foreign
[Music]
1900 okay we got a strong opponent here
Majid vs from Iran let's go now our
opponent might have bought the game
because no we're on our way C6 Karo Khan
so I flip-flopped quite a bit on what I
was going to recommend against the car
can of course the move is D4
I flip-flopped quite a bit on what I was
going to recommend in the Karo Khan as
my official official recommendation my
candidates were to recommend the
exchange car but I thought that was a
little bit boring and the repertoire
that I'm recommending is very tactical
it's it's for players who aren't who
don't mind sharp games who don't mind
learning some Theory and who want to
challenge their opponent in every
opening and there's really only one line
in the car that suits those purposes I
have played it before in the speed run
and I will preface it by saying that I
myself haven't reviewed my own fantasy
files in a while so I might be a little
bit Rusty I might mess something up but
that's okay we'll learn together and
this is the move F3 called the fantasy
variation
it was popularized in the early 2000s by
Alexander morosevic which should be a
name that is familiar to if you've spent
some time in the Chess World he doesn't
play much anymore but at one point I
think he was number two or number three
in the world he was high 2700s one of
the most creative players to have ever
lived and you should check out his games
I mean no matter what your style is you
should look at more Savage games
he was unbelievable he never became
world champion but you know just the the
Mikhail tall School uh really Mikhail
tall was his is his Idol he's still
alive that doesn't play Much Anymore
mostly just plays Blitz tournaments now
it is and he's declined quite a bit
um as Essie's gotten older but more
zevich popularized the fantasy which was
not taken seriously at the time I mean
people were laughing at this move
because to play F3 this early
against a sound opening like the Cairo
seems to violate a lot of principles but
if you look at it very concretely you
begin to realize that it's actually not
such a risky line it's not it's not as
risky as the king's Gambit for example
it's in a completely different category
E6 is considered to be Black's most
reputable response nowadays so our
opponent demonstrating some knowledge of
theory and we essentially play this like
a French the point of the movie six
first and foremost is to create a threat
what is black threatening well black is
threatening of course d-e-f-e and Queen
H for check so you might say oh let's go
G3
no no no you cannot afford to make any
more kingside pawn moves you need to
defend while developing
um and to defend while developing we
play the move uh Knight B1 C3 the point
is to reinforce the E4 pawn and
consequently to take the sting out of
the move Queen H4 which now meets with
G3
of course you might say well aren't we
allowing Bishop before just like in the
win our French which this line resembles
we do allow Bishop before and that is
indeed Black's main move the two main
moves are Bishop before and close second
is Knight F6 just like in the French and
Bishop before is our opponent's choice
so here white has a bunch of different
continuations
and I've analyzed a couple I'm actually
trying to remember my analysis right now
I know for a fact
that the most popular move here is
Bishop to D3
Bishop to D3 just a normal developing
move and you have this compact setup
Bishop d392 but but I
seem to remember
I seem to remember that I like the move
A3 here
let give me a second just to try to
remember my own file here A3 takes takes
D either it's a pawn sacrifice
you know what let's risk it I'm gonna go
A3 we're gonna go A3
and A3
on the surface should make sense to you
right it's a move that forces the bishop
to decide where it's going
now when you look at it more closely it
should strike you as a blunder we're
blundering Bishop takes C3 which our
opponent confidently plays and D takes
D4 isn't that the whole idea of the
movie six well what you should realize
is that black has given up his dark
squid bishop and if you look carefully
at Black's
position squares you should realize that
black has a lot of dark Square
weaknesses right there's D6 and E7 and
Black's position is kind of riddled with
dark Square weaknesses
but right now we're far removed from
that conversation we need to defend
against Queen H4 check and here there is
a computer move I admit that this is a
computer move this is virtually
impossible to come up with on your own
but once the move is played it begins to
make sense so it's not a bishop move
it's actually a night move and that
narrows it down to two well 92 runs into
e takes F3 that looks ugly it's not H4
we need to develop our pieces we must
develop our pieces the move is in fact
Knight to H3
and as a developing move it shouldn't
make sense we are developing a piece
we're getting closer to Castle and
kingside we're also a queen H4 check in
this particular situation is not
dangerous because we just have G3 but
the actual purpose of Knight H3 is to
prepare F take C4 that's the real reason
we play this move we're now threatening
to recapture the pawn because Queen H4
is then going to be met with Knight H3
to F2 protecting the E4 Pawn
so that's the specific reason we play
Knight H3 and not a bishop our opponent
continues to play correctly Queen A5 is
Theory move
and now if I remember correctly we must
defend this pawn and we have to do it
very very carefully so in the fantasy
you do make a bunch of moves sometimes
that are not positional in the sense
that they don't necessarily make sense
from a developmental standpoint but we
make them out of necessity
Queen D2 is awkward Queen D2 is awkward
it just it just doesn't look great we
still have to continue developing our
pieces so you come up with the idea of
Bishop to D2 but Bishop to D2 runs into
the very nasty move E3 deflecting the
bishop and then black drives in and
takes C3 with check and kind of forces
you to move the king away that's awkward
we play Bishop to B2 now is the bishop
currently bad on B2 no question about it
but later on we can play C4 and D5 so
the bishop to use the terminology I've
introduced in the previous Speed Run has
a lot of potential energy right it may
look terrible now but if we push the C
Pawn away it starts looking not quite so
terrible okay
so now if I remember correctly we are
supposed to take on e4
yeah our opponent is making All the
Right Moves he's going down my opening
file and this is already a very uncommon
line so I'm very impressed with our
opponent's theoretical knowledge thus
far and actually wait a second let me
think
I think the move is f take C4
but then black in response has the move
E5
so I'm trying to remember what the the
Crux of the line is there
it also could be Knight F2 no I'm pretty
sure we're supposed to now take the pawn
and black usually responds here with E5
and very impressive demonstration of
opening knowledge by our opponent
going down the the principled line and
then
taking on e4 so I kind of maybe jinxed
this move I think is dubious I think is
dubious so it's important here not to
get overwhelmed by what's going on
because there's a lot there's a lot
going on
but if you break down the position into
its component parts the moves are
actually quite natural from this point
on so first observation is that Knight
takes C3 is not a threat it's not a
threat because in response we can play
Queen to D2
attacking the Knight pinning the Knight
and winning the Knight because the queen
on A5 is unprotected
that tells us we don't need to make a
move that specifically protects C3 well
the next top priority is to make a
developing move
once I frame it like that the move
should be very obvious too and it's
Bishop F1 to D3 attacking the Knight
encouraging it to take on C3 and
preparing to Castle kingside
so the move is Bishop D3 and already
white has quite an initiative here
so again Knight C3 Queen D2 wins notice
that E5 is protected
our opponent drops the Knight back to F6
well
we continue our development which means
we need to Castle and castling does
the king to safety that's not the only
purpose of that move
the actually the main purpose of that
move is it puts the Rook on the
semi-openf file and that's one of the
appeals of playing the fantasy variation
you often get this openf file that you
can attack on and things get really
exciting really fast our opponent I
think is unaware of the danger that
awaits him he goes for a very kind of
slow move B6 preparing probably to
fianchetto or maybe play Bishop A6 but
we are just a couple of moves away from
smashing things open on the king side we
just need to figure out in what order to
do it and it's important not to get too
excited you still need to play based on
sound principles here so the move that
occurs to me first and this is
ultimately I think the move we are going
to play what did I say about this bishop
well this bishop is not very good as it
currently sits so it would make sense I
think to invest a Tempo to invest the
tempo and and push C4
and push C4 in order to be able to then
play D5 and fully open up the bishop and
if black continues to play without
developing then we are going to play D5
automatically because imagine we get C4
D5 and and black takes it we can
actually just take the Knight and take
again and have massive pressure on the
F7 Pawn so as an alternative the move
Queen F3 looks very nice I know some of
you proposed it's just a good move in
general maybe sliding the queen over to
G3 and hitting G7
in the same vein you could try Queen E1
and Queenie one is the advantage of
potentially lifting the queen up to H4
so I really really like Queen E1 here
actually it's a very mature move
but I think we're gonna play on theme
and we're gonna go C4
and C4 definitely is is irresistible to
me
and then on the next move well we can't
really play Queen E1 anymore because now
that invites a queen trade but we can
definitely go Queen F3
you can definitely go Queen F3 the funny
thing is the moment I played that move
I'm regretting a little bit not going
Queen E1 but in in these very promising
positions you often have multiple viable
attacking options but Knight bd7 okay
so this move connects the knights and
takes the sting out of D5 D5 no longer
looks impressive to me because then
black just plays cd5 and Bishop F6
Knight F6 the attack Fizzles out so I
think the time has come for us now
to invite the queen into the attack
let's bring the queen into the attack
let's get the lady involved
and let's go Queen F3 natural play now
am I worried at all about Black castling
Queen side a bit but the queen side
seems to be such a vulnerable area of
the board that I think will figure it
out if black Castle's Queen side we will
figure out how to get the king how to
hunt the king down on that side of the
board as well so again what was the
purpose of Queen F3 well it wasn't just
to hit the pawn the queen is aiming for
a particular destination and that
destination is G3 G3 is a super super
nice Square across a lot of fantasy
lines because it hits G7 it's just not
nicely clustered on the king side it's
out of the way of the other pieces right
when it was sitting on F3 it's kind of
in the way of The Rook here it's out of
the way of The Rook it's threatening to
take on G7 and it's inviting black to
make one of several very weakening moves
first of all I would love to see short
castle that probably loses on the spot
the move that a Grandmaster I think
would play here with black is long
Castle actually giving up G7 not an easy
thing to do our opponent plays it okay
so we'll get to the other moves later
then
and you know what I have had dinner
today
but I don't see a compelling reason
I don't see a compelling reason that we
can't take this pawn and this is I think
something that a lot of players have a
hard time with when they get into quote
unquote Attack Mode they somehow forget
that material exists and is an important
concept and is an important concept even
when you're attacking right when you're
attacking doesn't mean you can't take
stuff if it's free now Queen takes G7
certainly looks very scary well why does
it look scary it looks scary because it
opens up the G file so we need to
calculate Queen takes F6 Rook H to G8
but the queen weasels out through F7 and
it takes another Pawn along with it now
what can black try in that position who
can tell me a move that black can try
which intensifies the attack on the G2
pawn and this move might look very very
scary to you if you're trying to
visually it's the move C5 right two can
play at that game but C5 isn't as scary
as it looks because first of all first
of all we can simply defend the G2 Pawn
we can bring the Knight out to F4
where it protects G2 we could even play
the move D5 closing down the diagonal
so that looks interesting
although the position there becomes very
complicated because after D5 black can
actually play the crazy e takes D5 and
if we take the Knight on F6 black and
continue chomping and then he threatens
a bunch of different things
so I think we should take on G7
my intuition tells me that this is a
bluff
and that we will figure out a way to
counteract the attack on G2
let's go for it fingers crossed say your
prayers we're taking the pawn and I'm
not sure it's not like I've analyzed
this before and I'm playing it up for
the crowd I truly might look like a
complete fool here clearly our opponent
knows exactly what to do
because he responds instantly with Rook
G8 he might also not be taking us
seriously because we're 1400
but we're already up a pawn which is a
good thing we're attacking and we're up
a pawn
oh rookie eight that one I didn't see
that one I didn't see
but it doesn't actually threaten
anything does it oh but this is an
incredibly high level idea
this is an incredibly high level idea
because if Rook takes F6 which I thought
we would play
black plays Rook G to f8
and forces Our Queen away because the
knights defends throughout we can't
really take the we can't take the Rook
but we only have a queen and a piece I
didn't see that move at all Rook de-8
very quiet
what a move
okay well that means we need to just
play with our Queen on F7
and we need to figure out a move well
Bishop takes H7 is a move
but I don't know taking that pawn Rook
f8 Queen G7 maybe actually maybe we can
take H7
okay let's think
I actually have to think here I have an
interesting idea it's a very high level
move
it's a very high level move
so my worry my worry here
is that
black is going to go C5 that's basically
going to be his next move
so we need to do something
prophylactically to defend the pawn on
G2
and I had two ideas I had the idea of
going C5 ourselves to to bury the bishop
under a pile of rubble that's an
interesting thought C5
another idea is to play Knight F4 here
to defend G2 and the third idea is to
play Rook to F2
and Rook F2 has the aim of
well it has the aim of of Defending G2
with the Rook
I like C5 a lot yeah I like C5 as well
looks pretty good doesn't it
but there are some crazy lines where we
lose the queen I can't believe this
just a moment this is Bishop takes H7
actually might not be such a bad idea
here
yeah
let's give this a shot
while we're at it we'll take another
Pawn
now the point of this move has nothing
to do with winning a pawn
the purpose of this move could not be
further removed from I mean it's nice
that we take upon them we're now up two
Pawn so unless our opponent checkmates
us we're probably gonna win the game
okay this I don't understand at all he
gives us
an easy pass with the queen I guess he
wants C5
but C5 we go Rook F2 I mean why why is
that like the scariest thing in the
world you know
I don't know about Bishop takes H Knight
takes H7 he played that very quickly
okay C5 was the idea
now we definitely don't want to go G3
that's a ridiculously weakening move at
this point I don't want to go Knight F4
because after after the pawn on D4 is
eliminated Black's epon could push up to
E5 and attack the Knight
so
unless I'm missing something
catastrophic
which is entirely possible given
seemingly what seems to be our
opponent's iron-clad confidence in the
attack let's go Rook F2
this is and Queenie one not possible we
have the other Rook defending
so unless I've misjudged this and
there's some move here I think we're
fine
now fine in air quotes like their attack
is still very strong and when I say that
there's nothing obviously black has a
long-term attack too it's not like if we
don't get checkmated in two moves we're
safe we're actually not safe especially
if the wire opponent is playing Knight
F6 I saw that move but I thought we
could drop the queen back to D3
we definitely cannot take because then
The Rook takes on G2 and I'm going to
trust that our opponent has calculated
that so we need to move our Queen
and we should probably move it closer to
our King so Queen H4 comes to mind but
then it's a little bit offsides I would
be quite worried that the queen would be
on the side of the board I want it to be
directly contributing to the defensive
effort so let's bring it all the way
back to D3 and finally Our Queen is now
safe
yeah very sneaky opponent 94 is is looks
scary but again rookie two and where
exactly is the the killer blowing I
don't see it
yeah probably our opponent is going to
play CD
we're going to recapture I think with
our Bishop and probably our opponent is
going to play something like E5 would be
my guess
so we take with a bishop and not with
the queen because the queen on D3 is
well placed I don't want it to re-enter
the game like this and then walk into E5
and have to move again the queen is a
big liability when you're defending
because the queen can be used as fodder
for a well-timed tactic so you want to
keep the queen as safe as possible not
just your king okay obviously the move
is rookie too I'm speeding up a little
bit here we have to stay with the Rook
on the second rank the reason is if we
go anywhere else there there was Rook
takes G2 and Knight C5 Discovery winning
the queen
so we're starting to consolidate I think
and we're actually forcing our opponent
to spend a little bit longer
unless I'm missing again some
crazy idea here and there is a crazy
move
I realize that black and play E5 here
and after the bishop drops back to B2
um black has a very nasty check on C5
and if we if our King is for stage one
well then it walks into the diagonal and
there's also the possibility of a
smothered made potentially our Knight
NH3 is what stands between us and
smothered mate
so not a ton of good news in this
position I think if if our opponent
handles this like tall
yeah so
what's funny is if we end up losing our
opponent probably we'll
not waver in his belief that it was a
1400 after all
our opponent will yep beta 1400 just
another day at the office
but I have an idea
to defend against what I just said to
get what I just mentioned
yeah this would be the ultimate irony
so what's interesting I'll make a little
detour as our opponent is thinking is
that I remember a game this was a tragic
experience that I had I've never shared
this before so I had a game I was 1200
or 1300 this is one of my first ever
rated games well maybe I'd had 15 games
before this one it was my first ever
game at the Mechanics Institute chess
club in San Francisco which is the
oldest chess club one of the oldest
chess clubs in the country it's my
childhood chess club in San Francisco
there's now those chess clubs usually in
Charlotte there's the same thing there's
a tournament a weekly tournament it was
called Tuesday night marathon in San
Francisco and Charlotte it's Tuesday
night action there would be a club game
every Tuesday at 6 30 it would be USC up
rated so I played in those tournaments
in those Tuesday night marathons for
maybe like 11 12 years I would go to the
mechanics every single Tuesday now my
first ever game against the mechanics I
came my dad told me the pairing I sat
down he didn't tell me the rating of the
opponent so I had no idea if this guy's
800 or 1800 at that point like in my
career I was very affected by by ratings
so I played an absolutely brilliant game
like 2200 level wipe him off the board
and my rating at the time is like a
thousand
then toward the end of the game I get up
and I look at the pairing I realize the
pairings were just on the wall and I get
up and look at them
and my opponent is 1900. I see that my
opponent is 1900. and I almost peed
myself like I could not believe I was
being beating a 1900 because my highest
rated win at the time was maybe 1200.
and what do you think happened I did
something to the bed
five moves later I blundered it was
equal again and I ended up losing the
game
and it was unbelievably painful but the
effect of knowing your opponent's rating
Magnus was mentioning this in the SEC
interview
is immense like your play actually
changes and sometimes when you don't
know who you're playing maybe our
opponent is playing his actual best
strength because he's confident
so remember that everyone's human
ratings are completely relative I feel
like a 1200 A lot of the time and don't
let your opponent's rating dictate what
you do like that's a very sad way to
play
you should just play the same way
against anybody which is why we're
building good habits in the speeder and
I'm doing
maybe Overkill against lower rateds in
my technique and stuff and my
explanations but if you build those Good
Foundations you'll have the foundation
to beat higher it is later on in your
chess career
foreign
in the meantime our opponent has gone
into like
very deep tank
so in about three four minutes we'll
start thinking about how to exploit our
opponent's time pressure but for now he
still has plenty of time
yeah and nifa makes a great Point your
rating is not just your playing strength
but also your psychological strength
yeah I mean I know a lot of players who
just like go into shutdown mode the
moment they play someone who's 300
points higher rate at night
my students have struggled struggled
with this and this is something I
struggle to teach which is this like
mentality at some point you play an
opponent 300 400 points higher end you
just think you're going to lose and when
you get into that like there's no way
I'm winning this game mindset you are
actually going to lose every single game
against higher Raiders
there's a middle ground between coming
in and saying I'm gonna beat everybody
this guy sucks and then saying I'm gonna
lose because he's X points higher rated
than me
um okay our opponent's still thinking
he's down to seven and a half minutes
that's half his time
this is like a bit of a downside of the
15 plus 10 speed run is sometimes we we
just get into these like eight minute
things
but hopefully you've enjoyed the the
story
okay we can get back to the position in
sort of leisurely fashion
we are we have a threat white has a
threat in this position
what is White's threat
who can tell me what is White's threat
he might also have bad connection that's
totally possible
might have come up with a move move like
eight minutes ago yeah Rook takes C4
right getting two pieces for a rook and
essentially if we can eliminate the
bishop we eliminate the attack
so the threat is Rook take C4
black has different categories of moves
well I can create a counter threat which
is why I was worried about the move E5
counter threatening the bishop
so after E5 if we still play Rook E4
black will take the rook and then take
the bishop and be up in exchange now
that's a complicated line E5 Rook E4
Bishop E4 Queen E4 Ed we have a check on
A8 but the king drops up to C7 and there
are no further checks no further checks
your honor
so after E5 we have to move the bishop
we have two diagonals where we can move
it we can move it back to B2 that's what
I was discussing the problem with moving
it back to E3 is that black has this
weird quiet move Rook to d8
and suddenly the queen feels very very
uncomfortable there's only one square
Queen D3 to B3
and I don't know the queen on B3 it
walks into Knight to D2 and then from D2
then I can jump back to F3 with check
and maybe even back to H4 and attack G2
so black gets a lot of things going
there
that's why after E5 I wanted to go
Bishop B2 so that after Rook d8 what
additional squared does the White Queen
has have it has the E3 Square
it sits on E3 that's a very nice Square
it's invulnerable and it's preventing
Queen C5
so E5 I think is not that dangerous
black can also move the Knight away but
that definitely isn't dangerous
like Knight D6 we'll just play Rook hu
no Rook hu1 is bad
Knight D6 Rook H1 is better because
there's this Rook takes G2 move
Queen makes contact with the Rogue
deflection
so Knight D6 what are we gonna do
well we should try to find some sort of
General improving move
I really like the look of C5 in that
position weirdly enough
I like the look of C5
because after BC and Bishop it shuts
down the Queen's ability to access the
fifth Rank and that's really the only
way that Black's Queen is joining the
attack is through the fifth rank
so C5 looks really interesting in
response to Knight D6 Queen F5 of course
is a move
and finally our opponent plays E5
so we can respond very quickly because
we literally just spent seven minutes
talking about this move
I I genuinely think our opponent was
thinking
I I think there's a chance he was just
like legit thinking about a move Rook d8
this is exactly what we predicted
the queen now has the very nice E3
Square
okay and her opponent is back to the to
the PACE that we're used to
and he was attacked by a panther and
that that is perhaps the likeliest
theory
so again we have a bit of an issue where
it's hard for white to make progress
here
um and Knight D2 I was kind of expecting
that move
so first thing I see
is that the queen and the Knight are
aligned on the same diagonal so he's
walked into Bishop C3
but amazingly after Bishop C3 there's
this move Knight takes C4
our phone is playing like a genius
Knight takes C4
and if we take his Queen he takes Our
Queen and if we recapture G2 Falls with
check and then the bishop can be
captured so this might just be a
brilliant move
we can't play Queen takes E5 because of
Knight F3 check
oh my gosh
we can't play Queen C3
but then there's Queen C5 check
let's think what else can we do
no I don't want to sack The Exchange
because then black white gets no that's
losing no the second exchange is not an
option here
Knight G5 comes to mind as an
interesting way to block the G file
Knight G5 interesting Knight takes C4
Queen H3 check but then King B8 and our
Bishop hangs our Knight hangs Jesus
Bishop C3 Quincy five check on blue
okay
we're in trouble no he's out playing me
completely
I'm not playing this up
I the night I this is 90 just maybe I
move I would find in a classical game
but unlikely so let's continue thinking
maybe it's alireza
okay I need to think
like legit think
find something tricky here
now Bishop C3 we talked about Knight C4
hmm
thinking
and I can always speed up that's not
really a big worry
okay King H1 comes to mind also
King H1 curl up into a ball basically
King each one Rook G1
but at this no it also doesn't work
hmm
yeah I underestimated the attack
if I say something I'll be in big
trouble let's go King H1
feel like this prolongs the game the
most and increases the chance of a
mistake we'll check with the engine
afterward but
I'm
out of my league against this guy
it's just legit Out of My League
here
or queen B3
which move do we play Everything is
losing Queen B3
I think we have to go here
I think we have to go here and it's far
from obvious how black should proceed
it's far from obvious how black should
proceed here
and it's far from obvious that we're
dead lost I mean the position remains
very unclear but I can sense that the
game is not going in our Direction
um and I'm pretty pessimistic
but we had a game like this a couple
days ago and we we managed to pull it
out
so Queen D5 is what I'm actually hoping
for
most people I think in like the 1900
range would play Queen D5 they wouldn't
even think about trading
Queen D5 we play Rook G1 and that was
the point of King H1 this is a strong
defensive move because we walk into the
pin looks absurd but we're just making
space for The Rook to jump into you and
this is like a desperation strategy it's
I'm curled up into a ball and I can
barely move
but curling up into a ball can be like a
hard strategy to break down especially
in in a Blitz game
so
okay now there's no way that's the move
okay we take it
I don't even understand I mean there is
the idea of taking no but then Queen C4
what is this
is this a blunder
okay he takes and then he thinks that's
an interesting strategy
oh my God no it works
okay this is
this this smells wait a second
this this smells very very strange Rook
G1 Rook takes G2
Rook takes G2 and Rook G8 at the end and
I can't defend my own Rook
I'm stunned by this play
I'm stunned by this fly
no this is
this is absurd
Ean he thought on Queen D5
I'm sorry we will check and I will
always apply the same routine I never
accuse
almost period but not like first we look
at the engine it's entirely possible I
just freaking got outplayed I played a
360 Speed Run games
eventually I'm gonna lose a game and
like this might be the game that I
just didn't play well enough to beat you
know this 1900 in
but what is so suspicious to me is that
he took eight minutes before C5 before
E5 and then he rattled off one of the
most insane sequences I've ever seen
soap
so and here the problem is if I play
Rook G1 the the bishop hangs whereas if
I play Bishop C3 he has Knight E3 like
every move he has some crazy line and
that's always the feeling you get that
you're playing somebody who's so out of
your league
that it's like no matter what you do he
has he's had everything thought out for
ages
Julius Caesar when Julius Caesar was
stabbed he already saw and what is this
not taking the bishop he doesn't take
the bishop
he plays Rook G which is even better of
course because Rook GT Rook G2 and queen
D1 is coming to a theater near me
all right desperation Bishop D4
one last trap Queen D4 Rook G5
so this also totally might be a Smurf
and if it's a GM then I you know
I
am humbled this would still be very
strong play for a GM I'm in zugsvong I
just have to move my pawn and he goes
Knight E3 and wins
okay he takes first interesting I guess
he wants to
okay so you see that was that was
totally human move
At Last At Last I think I'm playing him
but we will check
I'm still gonna try wait is this is not
an obvious win now the most hilarious
thing of all time is gonna be if I win
this game or if I draw this game so just
let give me a second
if I draw this game this is going to be
the greatest moment in the speedrun ever
but I'm not going to because he has
Knight F5
so let's think
can I go the other way no crap I lose my
Pawn
that's the problem
wait wait I have an idea though
let's go
now here
try to confuse him
now this is another trap and he of
course sees D3
and will he see D2 that's the critical
move D2 and Knight G3 wins the pawn
no this guy is an absolute magician
absolute magician
let's see how he wins this
yeah I'm this is the strongest speedrun
opponent of all time and if you watch
him blunder his night
okay we're just waiting now this is
winnable by getting the pawn to A3 and
then knocking the king out
very strange technique so far
he's inching his Pawn along but slowly
but let's see if he knows not to bring
the pawn to A2 that would be a mistake
yeah he's not playing A4 wow King A4
okay wait a second
he's making this very interesting you
can see four
trying to set traps with my bear King
okay
oh oh yeah he got me there I guess I
should have gone King back to B2 wait
here
this can be a draw if he's not careful
oh my gosh
no it's winning
it's winning because of Knight C3 if it
was black to move here if it was white
to move again it would have been a draw
if it was my move here
it's a theoretical draw so he wins
actually by the skin of his teeth
wait he doesn't see it
oh my gosh
no it's not a draw what am I saying the
pawn has to be on A2 no no no the pawn
has to be on H2 I knew I was confusing
and he can move his King yeah this is
winning sorry if the pawn is on A2 then
it's a draw I'll show you what I mean
after the game I was wish I was thinking
wishfully
God this guy's taking forever to win
after and watch him stalemate me that
would be the
I feel like he's gonna still meet me
just get that good feeling
made in one
okay he finds it
okay yeah that was crazy
let's check the game we're getting some
bad luck in the speed run
let me
copy the game into chess space as we
usually do
but yeah that end game the way he played
in that end game it really did seem like
he had a a change had been made in
opponents from like 1 to 40 and then 40
to 80.
yeah and a lot of people who do trade
they do this very primitive method where
they cheat and then they play on their
own to eliminate you know to to lower
the accuracy but that that won't fool
you know the detection so okay so A3 is
a line yup not H3 that's the top move
so I wasn't misremembering
I was not misremembering Queen H2 is the
move so you can see we're following the
engine line so this is a mistake of
course and I knew that
here here here
C4 is correct
and bd7 is correct
here here we're we're playing like a
freaking engine and of course this was a
mistake it doesn't didn't evaluate
change the evaluation too much what does
Rook A1 I mean that's it's not a very
human move
okay
okay so this was not this was the second
move
okay now it's the first move okay
yep it's the basically top along with
Queen D2
takes takes C5 here mistake because of
Knight F6
top move
and then of course CD is top and 94
first and then E5
and of course Rook d8 second move good
enough as long as it's followed up by 92
which it is there's also the top move
and of course I blundered this
and Bishop G2 naturally followed by
Queen D5 is the refutation Rook G5 and
of course any normal human they wouldn't
take on B2 here they'd play the top move
Rook G8
and then he did
but then of course
a 1900 wouldn't see that 93 wins the
game on the spot no 1900 would trade
Queen seer
and then again start playing like an
engine
yeah no I mean this this to me
is
pretty blatant
barring the fact that he's actually a GM
even a GM I think would struggle to find
Knight T2 and stuff so I'm definitely
going to report him now I need people
who are watching like on YouTube to
understand that I I feel like this is a
very sensitive topic the concept like
GM's
ban you know GM's just like bullying
players and saying oh he's cheating he's
cheating but I want to take the fact
that I'm a GM out of the equation I
showed you why I'm suspicious right it
was literally he made one mistake in the
opening and then he makes 25 top engine
moves in a row
and I got the feeling that I was just
getting blown out of the water and then
he makes a move nobody would ever play
and then it has to and then spends like
50 moves winning the end game so
a lot of a lot of signs pointing one way
and only on the basis of that am I going
to report him
um extremely
suspicious play starting
move
13.
25 or so top engine moves
to insane ideas included followed by
clear play at a significantly lower
level for the rest of the game
yeah I guess I'll block him as well
yeah so we've we have played confirmed
cheaters a couple times so we'll see
what chess.com decides and if they
decided didn't she then I will take my
words back
and uh I will accept the results like
that's I feel like that's how to handle
it but let's actually look at the game
because I think my accuracy was not bad
at all I don't think I played a terrible
game at all
um I just made like one or two big
mistakes in in the critical tactical
position
so as I was saying earlier and we'll
actually look in chess space because we
again need to use the engine here
there's a lot of very complicated lines
um well I appreciate people giving me
the benefit of the doubt so we'll skip
right to this position what I mentioned
to you before about the fantasy I'll
give you an introduction to the fantasy
some other time I'll give you the
overview but this is a very specific
kind of game so we'll we'll go straight
into this line so the move Knight F6
here
if you want if you're comfortable
playing a knight C3 French you can
actually transpose into the French with
E5 and F4 and this is the Stein it's
French you've just transposed directly
into it
but white doesn't have to play E5
um white can also play I think the
engine likes to move Bishop D3 white has
a bunch of these Sidelines here that you
can investigate but realistically the
movie 5 is topical and for that reason
almost nobody I mean not a lot of people
play Knight F6
so Bishop B4 A3 if Bishop A5 then I
think the move I decided on was Bishop
D3 this is a pawn sacrifice
technically but you get absolutely like
massive development here with Knight F3
and Black's position just kind of falls
apart here if black takes another Pawn
then you have three pieces developed
black is zero
and I mean
I mean this position just sucks Queen E2
then Bishop B4 you can play
Bishop can be stuck onto D6 I mean it's
it's just a massive Initiative for white
and if the queen moves away
if the queen moves away the engine likes
to solidify the center with E5 also open
up the bishop setting up potential Greek
gift sacrifices
foreign
is very promising GMS usually go like 97
here but then white can go Knight E2 and
you get this very like compact
development
and Black's position is slightly passive
here it's like solid for black
but I think it's more fun for white to
play these types of positions you can go
Bishop G5 you can go Bishop E3
you can play on both sides of the board
I think you can bring your queen into
the game you can push the F Pawn it's
like I would suggest that if you want to
play the Fantasy well you should analyze
with the engine in a position like this
for like 30 45 minutes just like move
pieces around see what happens try to
understand the ideas
and that's ultimately like what you do
to prepare yourself for Middle games so
our opponent played the topical line
takes takes Knight H3 which I explained
here here Knight F6 Fe and now I was
shocked that he didn't play E5 which is
again a move I would expect the 1900 to
play
and here the lines get pretty crazy so
white plays Bishop D3
sacrificing the pawn on D4 and then
moves the queen up to D2
the point of this move is to encourage
black to play DC you're trying to lure
black into taking these pawns so that
the dark squared Bishop becomes the
monster that it's supposed to be and
again it's one of those situations where
we've sacked upon but we have a big
initiative
Queen C7 you can jump with the Knight
H6 E5 counter-attacking black snipe and
then whitesnike can slink back to E4
and look at this line Castle's Knight F6
check
just sick lines all over the fantasy GF
Queen H6
with unstoppable Checkmate essentially
if the king moves away then we just take
the Knight we eliminate Black's only
strong piece and look at I mean looking
for Bishops like a rook this is like
crushing
so some cool lines here
but for that reason black is supposed to
eliminate the Knight
and the engine does tell black to take
and apparently black is okay here
another case where like holy smokes I
would be terrified to play this position
with black but apparently the best that
white can do is some sort of repetition
but realistically I would just Castle
here and enjoy my life with white two
bishops get the Rook into the game
black is again supposed to play like an
engine here I'm sure our opponent will
would uh navigate this flawlessly
yeah and more evidence seems to be
coming out who's 1100 three months ago
yeah okay
I think we'll
leave it to chess.com so this line from
a practical perspective is incredibly
promising our opponent plays Knight E4
allowing this this absolutely massive
development
and after B6 we correctly were deciding
between these two moves and the engine
says to play them interchangeably so C4
and queen F3
and even Queen G3 is correct so we get
to the next critical moment which is
here
now I think most people in the 1900
range would be tempted to play a move
like G6 which essentially loses after D5
if black Castle's King side then again I
was planning D5 but apparently that's
not the best move because of E5 this
closes down the diagonal so according to
the engine oh Bishop C3 is sexy oh that
is quite the move
takes we have Bishop H7
if the queen skips over to the other
side of the board we lift our Rook up to
H4 and then we trap it
look at these lines Queen A4 Rook F6
Knight F6 and D5 and the difference
between this D5 and that D5 is that
black E5 is futile because of Bishop E5
E5 is futile so black has to move the
Knight away and then the attack
Queen H3 wow oh
my God Queen H6 got when you analyze at
the engine just find these like
disgusting ideas all the time
then it becomes addicting
just crazy attacking concept here
but look I mean look at this attack look
at Black's position now you shouldn't
have any any trouble understanding that
white is winning here that's how
intuition works right you're not
calculating you're just looking at the
position saying Black's got nothing in
the game it's over
and if King h8 you can play oops sorry
takes takes Queen H4 F5 check get in
there and then just Queen H6 easy clap
so this is a pretty straightforward
attacking line
in any case castle short
was not the way to go
so Castle's Queen side is a super high
level decision by our opponent to
realize that you are giving away this
very important pawn and that's the only
way to stay afloat now look at the
engine's recommendation here Rook a to
E1 it's just saying improve your
position don't commit to anything and
black has no good moves so I was worried
that black would go C5 but we can just
plug the diagonal and jump into G5 and
now you understand why the engine wanted
us to put the Rook on E2 on E1
because now it can infiltrate to E7
so this is what engines do they make
this very mysterious move and you're
like why why here why E1 why not D1 and
it only reveals itself in response to
some opponent some particular move in
this case C5
so let's say black plays Rook GA now
again we go Knight G5
we try to induce Rick fate and we
actually play Bishop takes H7
and oh my god look Bishop G6 no that's
why we eliminated the pawn so that after
96 there was Unstoppable Checkmate on C7
B5 Bishop C3 Queen B6 C5 get off the
diagonal get off the diagonal so we can
play Queen C7
I mean come on yeah it's fun to analyze
with an engine when you got like a guide
you know and I I feel like I'm a good
guide because I can spot the cool lines
really fast
and if Knight H7 you play Knight H7
attacking The Rook
The Rook has to move and Black's
construction just collapses here notice
the Rook anyway is defended
so Rook 81 what if black plays H6 oh now
we take
and now if you go down the same line as
well black can't even play the same
movies in the game okay rookie eight
Queen F7 yeah
so this with the Rook on E1 none of
Black's ideas tend to work
oh because of rookie six uh-huh so the
reason the Rook honey one here is so
important is because we will take the
pawn given the opportunity and then we
can meet C5 with D5 and we close the
diagonal permanently
so it was necessary to thrown but Queen
G7 is not a big mistake so our opponent
finds this move another strange move
that the computer only starts
appreciating
at a high depth
or maybe not it's the second best move
Queen D2 was best and then rookie 8. so
similar type of idea
because this keeps
keep fine and it makes it very hard for
white to find a move so D5 is tempting
but there's this check on C5 and then CD
and if we take on F6 black plays DC
and there's a mate thread on G2 and the
bishop is lost in white collapses so if
we play Rook F6 then Rook gf8 another
crazy idea forcing the queen away and
then black takes the entire Rook away
so we decided on Bishop H7 she's a very
panicky move very panicky move it gives
away a very important piece
according to the engine just Rook 81 is
best keep the tension I panicked and if
C5 then D5
takes takes
yeah just Bishop F6 wins the piece the
rook's no longer on G8
so yeah Rook A1 makes perfect sense I
decided to grab the other Pawn
and after C5 already the situation is
quite Dire from a human standpoint
okay the engine move is crazy D5 Ed and
Rook a E1 putting the Rook on pre
because of the Rook on sorry because of
the Rook on G8 being hanging as well but
again this rookie one the engine loves
putting the Rook on E1 here we played
Rook F2 Knight F6 another crazy move
takes here and here is totally crushing
also not like mate but just a crushing
attack
um so this is a maneuver but a lot of
people would go 94 here and after rookie
two the Knight has to jump back this
would be very impulsive our opponent
correctly takes first and only now plays
Knight E4 and the difference is that
black has this movie five
Bishop B2 and now rook d8 and Knight D2
at the end which is a very hard to
understand move but the point is it
threatens the pawn and it opens the
diagonal for Black's other pieces it
just creates too much tension in White's
position too much strain
so here are some of the lines that I
calculated before deciding that we're
lost if Queen C3 then check
here here
and at the end of this line Queen C6
check is winning because King F2 King G3
both run into the fork and King G1 Rook
G8 is similarly crushing
so that's fails Bishop C3 is what we
started with this is the reason most
people would refute Knight D2 But Here
There is Knight takes C4
take take and now if we play rookie
three black plays Rook G2 and ba and
this end game is totally lost because
just look at it I mean White's losing
everything the other rook's coming in so
according to the engine the only chance
would have just been to play G3 here I
didn't even think about this move and it
is losing it is losing for white black
has too much activity too many squares
the attack persists into the end game so
this is miserable but the way I played
it it loses on the spot but only two
this bishop G2 idea crazy
and after Queen D5 the point is that
after Rook G1 this is what I missed take
take Rook G8 no way to defend the Rook
with the queen somehow all the squares
are taken away
Knight G5 Rook G5
this is what it feels like to play an
engine everything has been accounted for
so I desperately played Knight G5 to get
the queen over which is a nice idea but
we're too tied up here everything is
falling now any human would take on B2 I
feel just take the bishop but our
opponent continued putting pressure with
Rook G8
and okay the rest is is history and then
here who doesn't play Knight E3
who takes here which incidentally it's
very close to being a draw if if black
plays
if we go here I think the only way to
win is basically to go Knight F5 and
Knight G3 black has to eliminate this
Pawn
and then at the very end I was
delusional I apologize for that
what I was confusing this with
think you'll forgive me if the pawn is
on A2 this is already a draw this is a
draw because the black king never gets
out of the of the Trap and the reason it
never gets out of the Trap is if you had
this exact position with white to move
right if this position with white to
move black would be winning because the
king can't go back to C1 and wherever it
goes black moves out and promotes so
something worth remembering that with
with like the right side to move this is
a drop like a zero progress to make the
Knight cannot triangulate the Knight
mathematically cannot lose Tempe and so
it just goes between C1 and C2 we were
very close to this like our opponent got
it very very close but realized that
this is just winning easily by forcing
the white king out of the shell or
stepping back to B3 and playing A2 and
Knight C2
um
but it took a it took him like 30 moves
longer than it should have
so yeah amazing game
and I don't remember who said it but
somebody May mentioned that like some of
the most beautiful games in the world in
history are like games where someone
cheated it's like you produce these
ridiculous ideas so this was amazing
player by our opponent he's going to get
investigated but you know where I stand
hopefully you found the arguments to be
reasonable and
you know trust.com will will set the
record straight whether he cheated or
not and like I said if it turns out he
didn't I'll uh I'll make that clear in
the next Speed Run game
so
yeah so it's possible he's GM
um and any smurfing and topaz was not
cheating there is a chance that he's not
cheating
um but I feel like I really have to make
that clear
really have to make that clear
because people are very sensitive now to
false accusations and GMS kind of using
their authority to accuse people so
hopefully you don't feel like I'm doing
that
um thank you everybody hope you enjoyed
the game
um nonetheless I think it was
instructive
thank you everybody
thank you for hanging out I'll see you
tomorrow bye
[Music]